RG 003, New London County Court African Americans and People of Color Collection
Connecticut State Library
19Box 2, folders 8, 9, 11. New London diarist Joshua Hempstead says the following about the incident, "Andrew Palmes turned Adm Roger's wife and family out of doors & flung all their household goods ovut over the fence out Side." "Diary of Joshua Hempstead," Collections of the New London County Historical Society, Vol. 1 (New London: The New London County Historical Society, 1901), 427.
20RG 002, Rejected Bills, African Americans, Box 2, folder 3, CSL. They argued in the petition that they were "descendants of African Citizens brought to this Country against their will," their ancestors were enslaved, and that they "in the midst of the most mortifying discouragements have acquired some property." Since the Constitution of 1818 prohibited them "form attaining the high character of Electors or being represented in the Legislature," justice demanded that they be exempted from taxation.
21Mattison v. Cogswell, Nov. 1783, Box 3, folder 25.
22Cogswell v. Moody, Feb. 1786, Box 3, folder 33.
23Robert Crary v. Benadum Gallup, Dec. 1788, Box 3, folder 37.
24Pero Moody v. William Waters and Russel Rose, Mar. 1823, Box 6, folder 16.
25W. Jeffrey Bolster, "Letters by African American Sailors, 1799-1814," William and Mary Quarterly, Third Series, Vol. LXIV, No. 1 (January 2007): 177. This letter from John Backus to Abraham Bishop was written on Oct. 28, 1811.
26Nathaniel Otis v. Isaac Rogers, Nov. 1799, Box 3, folder 24. The white Isaac Rogers lived in a part of New London called Great Neck that became part of Waterford when that town was incorporated in Oct. 1801.
27Sept. 1701, Box 1, folder 1.
28Nov. 1704, Box 1, folder 1. The verdict is not known due to the fact that no Trials volume exists for the years 1704-1710.
29Robert Jacklin v. Sarah Wright, Nov. 1723, Box 1, folder 15; Sarah Wright v. Robert Jacklin, Nov. 1723, Box 1, folder 15; Robert Jacklin v. Samuel Wright, June 1724, Box 1, folder 17, Robert Jacklin v. Samuel Wright, Aug. 1726, Box 1, folder 23, Adam Rogers Junr v. John Rogers, Nov. 1739, Box 1, folder 45; and Cudgo Wanton v. Zebulon Caples, June 1770, Box 3, folder 6.
30June 1720, Box 1, folder 11.
31Feb. 1731, Box 1, folder 35.
32Feb. 1753, Box 2, folder 17. Poor whites, in addition to poor African Americans, were assigned to service, often of the plaintiff, for a period of time to cover debts owed.
33Ralph Isham Petition, Dec. 1813, Box 5, folder 20; James Lee v. John Amy, Dec. 1813, Box 5, folder 21.
34Peggy Sansom v. Thomas Steward, Nov. 1835, Box 7, folder 26; Alfred P. Williams v. Ephraim Williams, Nov. 1835, Box 7, folder 27.
35Feb. 1740, Box 2, folder 1.
36Abiel Cheney v. Samuel Hull, June 1763, Box 2, folder 34; Ebenezer Fitch v. Samuel Hull, June 1763, Box 2, folder 35; David Hosmer v. Samuel Hull, Ibid; Simon Lothrop v. Samuel Hull, Ibid; Simon Lothrop v. Samuel Hull, June 1763, Box 2, folder 36; John Simson v. Samuel Hull, Ibid.
37June 1774, Box 3, folder 17.
38Nov. 1774, Box 3, folder 17.
39June 1757, Box 2, folder 23.
40Nov. 1722, Box 1, folder 13.
41June 1735, Box 1, folder 40. The plaintiff failed to appear at court.
42Nov. 1752, Box 2, folder 16.
43Nov. 1748, Box 2, folder 13.
44Nov. 1737, Box 1, folder 44.
45Nov. 1757, Box 2, folder 24.
46Feb. 1800, Box 4, folder 35.
47Dec. 1789, Box 3, folder 39
48Feb. 1731, Box 1, folder 34.
49June 1743, Box 2, folder 6.
50June 1729, Box 1, folder 31.
51Nov. 1767, Box 3, folder 1.
52New London County, County Court, Records, Trials, Vol. 21, Feb. 1749/50, no. 52; Feb. 1750, Box 2, folder 14. Additional information can be found in the Costs and Summons for Evidence series of Papers by Subject. Box 11, folder 16; Box 13, folder 16.
53In this instance, servant meant hired servant and not slave.
54Feb. 1741, Box 2, folder 14.
55For these figures, not distinction is made between burglary, a crime that involves entering a building and stealing property there from, and theft
56Apr. 1815, Box 5, folder 26.
57State v. George Derry, Nov. 1830, Box 7, folder 7.
58State v. Horace Thompson, Nov. 1845, Box 9, folder 9.
59June 1773, Box 3, folder 13.
60Nov. 1737, Box 1, folder 44.
61Prince Williams v. Nathan Crary, Jr., June 1791, Box 4, folder 1.
62State v. Wheeler Morgan, Nov. 1836, Box 7, folder 30.
63State v. George Jackson, Nov. 1845, Box 9, folder 8. Three other people of color were called as witnesses; Minerva Robbins, Freelove Brighton, and Mrs. Anderson.
64Nov. 1852, Box 11, folder 1.
65State v. Prince Williams, Nov. 1842, Box 8, folder 28; State v. Sarah Richards, June 1850, Box 10, folder 15.
66State v. Josephine Mead, June 1851, Box 10, folder 23; State v. Henry Benton, June 1851, Box 10, folder 24. All the prosecutions for adultery occurred between the years 1835-51.
67Thankful Warris v. Samuel W. Perkins, Mar. 1824; Box 6, folder 22; State v. James Guy, Nov. 1847, Box 9, folder 18.
68State v. Lemuel Henry, Feb. 1846, Box 9, folder 10; Ibid, Feb. 1847, Box 9, folder 15; Ibid, June 1847, Box 9, folders 16-17.
69State v. Benjamin Bacon, Nov. 1853, Box 11, folders 2-3.
70Jeremiah Tracy v. Pero Moody, June 1897, Box 5, folder 2.
71John Burwell, Augustus Perkins & Samuel Freeman v. Levi Meeds, Dec. 1807, Box 5, folder 3.
72State v. Zebulon Parkis, Jr., Feb. 1845, Box 9, folder 7.
73State v. Robbins Babcock, Dec. 1848, Box 9, folder 29.
74Feb. 1755, Box 2, folder 19. The second case, found with June 1755 court records, concerns a 1753 prosecution of Rogers for cruelty to his "Negro boy" Sharper and two adults, Cato and Simon. A New London justice of the peace determined that Rogers "hath Cruelly Used the sd. Cato and Simon" and bound him over for trial before the county court. In June 1755, Rogers' bonds were called out and he was dismissed after paying court costs of £10-15-2. June 1755, Box 2, folder 20.
75June 1753, Box 2, folder 18.
76In one case he is called Titus "a free Molato Man or Mustee," in the second Titus Mando, and a "Negro Boy Named Titus" in the third.
77June 1762, Box 2, folder 32; June 1763, Box 2, folder 37; Nov. 1764, Box 2, folder 42. The General Assembly, sitting as the colony's Supreme Court, heard the case, but declined to overturn the verdict. Connecticut Archives, Revolutionary War, 1st Series, Vol. 37, 199-204.
78State v. Peggy Sansom, Benjamin Burton, John Rhodes, Lucy Rhodes & John Smith, Nov. 1831, Box 7, folder 12.
79State v. William Johnson, Felix Ruggles, James Peckham, Luther Peckham, William H. Brown "and divers other persons," Nov. 1842, Box 9, folder 27. For a related case, see Box 9, folder 29.
80New London County, County Court, Trials, Vol. 24, Nov. 1763, no. 7; Ibid, Files, Nov. 1763, Box 129, folder 8, no. 7.
81Feb. 1764, Box 2, folder 41.
82Jonah Witter v. Stephen Young & David Lewis, Jr., Dec. 1813, Box 5, folder 20; Joseph Noyes v. Charles Smith, Dec. 1813, Box 5, folder 21.
83Mar. 1824, Box 6, folder 22.
84Lydia Bulkeley v. Oliver Raymond, June 1835, Box 7, folder 23.
85Costs, Jack Bennet, Dec. 1819; James Robbins, Mar. 1820, Box 11, folder 26.
86Ibid, Feb. 1840, Box 12, folder 3.
87Index of Revolutionary War Pension Applications in the National Archives, Bicentennial Edition (Revised & Enlarged) (Washington, D.C.: National Genealogical Society, 1976), x.
88Pensions, Revolutionary War, Peter Peters, June 1820, Box 13, folder 8.
89Summons for Evidence, June 1735, Box 13, folder 14; Feb. 1756, Box 13, folder 18.
90Conservators and Guardians, Thomas Halsey, Box 11 folder 8.
91Costs, Feb. 1750, Box 11, folder 16; Summons for Evidence, Box 13, folder 16.
92Costs, June 1761, Box 11, folder 18.
93Executions, Pero Moody v. Isaac S. Moody, June 1818, Box 12, folder 36.
94Executions, State v. Oliver H. Perry Lewis, June 1836, Box 12, folder 46.
Related Material
Additional information can be found in Dockets and Trials. The volumes of records for Trials sometimes contain more information, particularly for the period before 1720. Documentation for cases that were appealed can be found the records for the Superior Court of New London County.
Database of Cases
A database for the 1,191 records involving people of color from New London County is included in this collection. The database contains fields for surname and first name, if known, residence, date of court session, case name, and subject. It can be accessed by researchers from the Connecticut State Library website at:.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. County Court (New London County)
Subjects:
County courts -- Connecticut -- New London County -- History; African Americans -- Connecticut -- History -- 18th century; Connecticut. County Court (New London County) -- History; Connecticut. Judicial Dept. -- History; Connecticut -- History -- Sources; New London County African Americans Collection
Document Types:
Civil court records; Criminal Court records; Judicial records
Restrictions on Access
This artificial collection of materials devoted to African Americans appearing before the New London County Court consists of photocopies of original documents. All originals have been restricted.
See the policy.
Provenance
The records of the New London County Court were transferred to the Connecticut State Library in 1921.
Container List
- 1. Files
  - 1701 September - 1739 June (Box 1, Folder 1-46)
  - 1739 November - 1767 June (Box 2, Folder 1-45)
  - 1767 November - 1774 November (Box 3, Folder 1-17)
  - 1781 November - 1791 June (Box 3, Folder 18-43)
  - 1791 June - 1806 December (Box 4, Folder 1-44)
  - 1806 December - 1819 June (Box 5, Folder 1-42)
  - 1819 June - 1827 November (Box 6, Folder 1-35)
  - 1827 November - 1838 June (Box 7, Folder 1-34)
  - 1838 June - 1843 November (Box 8, Folder 1-32)
  - 1844 February - 1849 June (Box 9, Folder 1-32)
  - 1849 June - 1852 November (Box 10, Folder 1-30)
  - 1852 November - 1854 November (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
- 2. Papers by Subject
  - Confiscated Estates (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Conservators and Guardians (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
  - Costs (Box 11, Folder 8-46)
  - Costs (Box 12, Folder 1-16)
  - Court Expenses (Box 12, Folder 17-19)
  - Executions (Box 12, Folder 20-47)
  - Executions (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
  - Pensions, Revolutionary War (Box 13, Folder 4-11)
  - Summons for Evidence (Box 13, Folder 11-20)